Inventory of the James Barron Papers (1) 1776-1899
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
- Box 7, 1825-1827. (Box-folder 7:1-78)
  - Letter - Captain Kenyon, Philadelphia, to Commodore James Barron, Norfolk, 13 October 1825., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 7:40)
    Re: verbal message given as ships passed, but not heard.
  - Letter - James Maury, Liverpool, to James Barron, 24 October 1825., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 7:41)
    "We all rejoiced in what must have been so gratifying to yourself after so long and so painful a period of suspense."
  - Report - T.U. Wiesenthal, Late Surgeon, U.S. Ship Hornet, to Sam[uel] L[ewis] Southard, 1 November 1825., 3 pages. Cop of ALS. (Box-folder 7:42)
    Forwarded to Captain Edmund P. Kennedy then to James Barron. A report of valuable use of the bellows invented by Barron in changing air below decks and in the control of disease there.
  - Request - Richard Kennon, Norfolk, to Comdr. James Barron, Gosport Navy Yard, 5 November 1825., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 7:43)
    Request for leave of absence.
  - Report - Richard Kennon to Com. James Barron, 20 November 1825., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 7:44)
    Report on return from his leave.
  - Letter - C.W. Goldsborough, Washington, to Commre. James Barron, Gosport, Virginia, 11 November 1825., 2 pages. ALS, Encl. (Box-folder 7:45)
    Re: the use of the title, "Commodore" honorary since the Navy has no such rank.
  - Letter - Miles King, Norfolk, to Commodore James Barron, Navy Yard, Gosport, 3 December 1825., 1 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 7:46)
    Re: transportation of powder to Richmond.
  - Letter - Francis Grice, U.S. Navy Yard, Gosport, to James Barron, Commander, Navy Yard, 23 January 1826., 1 page. Cop of AL. (Box-folder 7:47)
    Defense of the Navy Constructor at the Yard.
  - Letter - Benjamin King, Washington, to Comdr. James Barron, Norfolk, 17 April 1826., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 7:48)
    Re: the ventilation on ships and suggestions for improvements.
  - Letter - R.S., Washington, to [James] B[arron], 20 April 1826., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 7:49)
    Report of speech by John Randolph in which he "abused everybody" including Barron in regard to the Chesapeake affair and the duel with Decatur. Added note: "Burn it as soon as you read it."
  - Letter - Beverly Kennon, U.S. Frigate U. States, Callas, to Commodore [James] Barron, Norfolk, 5 May 1826., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 7:50)
    Re: his cruise, Naval discipline, and injustice the President's message recommending a Naval Academy. Re: South American politics and the fall of Callas.
  - Letter - H. Eckford, New York, to Commodore James Barron, Norfolk, 20 May 1826., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 7:51)
    Re: the completion of ships being built to order.
  - Letter - A. McLane, Washington, to James Barron, Gosport, Virginia, 1 July 1826., pages. ALS. (Box-folder 7:52)
    Re: the build-up of the Navy.
  - Report - L. Warrington, U.S. Ship Constellation, near Pensacola, to Commodore James Barron, commanding U.S. Navy Yard, Norfolk, 20 July 1826., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 7:53)
    Report that all is quiet in that area, that no piracies are heard of.
  - Letters - Samuel Southard, Navy Department, to Commre. James Barron, commanding the U.S. Navy Yard, Gosport, Virginia, July 1826., 2 letters. ALsS. (Box-folder 7:54)
    Correspondence regarding the new type wooden docks and new type dry docks, invented by Barron.
  - Letter - James Barron, Philadelphia, to Mrs. Jane Hope, Norfolk. 20 August 1826., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 7:55)
    Re: his invention of a new type of dock.
  - Invitation - E. Shubrick to Commodore [James] Barron, Walnut St., [Philadelphia], 7 October 1826., ALS. (Box-folder 7:56)
    Invitation to dinner.
  - Letter - M.C. Stephens, Newbern, to Com. James Barron, Norfolk, 5 November 1826., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 7:57)
    Re: the estate of John B. Osborn, grandson of David Barron.
  - Social Note - T. Gatewood, Norfolk, to Commodore James Barron, Philadelphia, 26 November 1826., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 7:58)
    Social news.
  - Letter - C.K. Davis, ship Bill of Lading on "Emily Davis" from Philadelphia to Com. James Barron, Norfolk, Virginia, 2 December 1826., 1 page. PADS. (Box-folder 7:59)
  - Letter - James Barron, Gosport, to Anderson Warfield, Baltimore, 7 December 1826., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 7:60)
    Declining to get involved in more controversy concerning his treatment by the Navy in the past years.
  - Recommendation - W.H. Harrison, Washington, to James Barron, Norfolk, 29 December 1826., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 7:61)
    A recommendation of the bearer, T.H. Yateman.
  - Copybook of letters - exchanged by James Barron with Commo. William Bainbridge, President of the Navy Board, Washington, with Charles W. Goldsborough, Secretary of the Board of Navy command and Sam[ue]l L. Southard, Secretary of the Navy, 1826-1827., Cop of AL. (Box-folder 7:62)
    Relating to affairs of the Navy Yard, Gosport, Virginia.
  - Recommendation - T. Gatewood, Norfolk, to Commodore James Barron, Philadelphia, 28 March 1827., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 7:63)
    Re: a recommendation to the Treasury Department relative to a "system of telegraph for the United States."
  - Letter - Emma Prevost, Philadelphia, to Commodore James Barron, Norfolk, 1 April 1827., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 7:64)
    Re: the "automatic chess player."
  - Letter - P. Hansen, St. Croix, to Captain Choate, Schooner Lafayette, St. Croix, 20 April 1827., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 7:65)
    Sending a greeting to Commo. Barron from his friends in Denmark.
  - Letter - Tench Ringold, Washington, to Commodore James Barron, U.S. Navy Yard, Gosport, Virginia, 2 May 1827., 2 page. ALS. (Box-folder 7:66)
    Re: a Mr. Butler.
  - Letter - T. Gatewood, Norfolk, to Commodore James Barron, Philadelphia, 16 June 1827., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 7:67)
    Re: social news of Norfolk.
  - Letter - W.J. Kripgans, Cape Hatteras, to Commodore James Barron, Gosport, Virginia, 25 June 1827., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 7:68)
    Re: shipping around the Cape.
  - Letter - Andrew Jackson, Hermitage, to Capt. E.P. Kennedy, Norfolk, 30 June 1827., 2 pages. Cop of AL. (Box-folder 7:69)
    Accepting position of godfather to Kennedy's son and approving the choice of James Barron as his proxy; statement of his high regard for the Navy.
  - Letter - Capt. John Gallagher, Navy Yard, Charleston, [Massachuetts], to Commodore James Barron, commanding Navy Yard, Gosport, Virginia, 8 June 1827., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 7:70)
    Family and Naval news.
  - Letter - Capt. John Gallagher, Charleston, [Massachuetts], to Commodore James Barron, Gosport, Virginia, 3 July 1827., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 7:71)
    Re: the log boats invented by Barron.
  - Request - L. Warrington to Commodore James Barron, U.S. Navy Yard, Norfolk, 20 July 1827., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 7:72)
    Request for the service of Coxwain Parker, sympathy at death of Lieut. Tuttle.
  - Invitation - Mrs. Bainbridge to Comdr. [James] Barron, 27 July 1827., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 7:73)
    Invitation to tea.
  - Letter - E.P. Kennedy, Navy Yard, Gosport, to Comdr. Ja[me]s Barron, Navy Yard, Gosport, 8 August 1827., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 7:74)
    Re: the success of the ventilating bellows invented by Barron.
  - Letter - Thomas Williamson, U.S. Naval Hospital, Gosport, Virginia, to Commodore James Barron, Gosport, Virginia, 16 August 1827., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 7:75)
    A recommendation that he leave the area in the "sickly season" for the sake of his health.
  - Appointment - Comdr. Warrington, Office of the Naval Command, to Commodore James Barron, U.S. Navy Yard, Gosport, Virginia, 17 October 1827., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 7:76)
    Re: an appointment marked "Private."
  - Letter - J.D. Elliott, Philadelphia, to Como. James Barron, Norfolk, 20 November 1827., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 7:77)
    Re: personal and Naval affairs.
  - Letter - J.H. Eaton and M. Timberlake, Washington City, to Capt. James Barron, Norfolk, Virginia, 13 December 1827., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 7:78)
    Re: personal matters.
  Series 8: Box 8
- Box 8, 1828-1831., Correspondence of the years 1828-1831 includes several letters from Andrew Jackson and comments in other letters on his election as President. One group of letters exchanged between Barron, Dr. Philip Barraud, and Jackson concern the threat of the dismissal of Barraud from Director of a Government Hospital under the exercise of the "Spoils System." Included is a letter from Mary Holt regarding Barron's romantic attachment to another, which led to his second marriage; an exchange of letters with James Monroe who was aboard a steamship stuck in the Potomac to which Barron sent relief; letters from Capt. Edm. P. Kennedy, Washington, D.C., and Gen'l Winfield Scott, New York; and correspondence concerning Barron's inventions-the movable crane, ships ventilators, a fan, and a plough. In 1828, Barron was appointed commander of the Pacific Fleet, a position from which he requested release due to his involvement in establishing claims for bounty lands from his father's Revolutionary War service; in 1831 he accepted a return to the command of the Philadelphia Naval Yard. Included are articles on Naval affairs written for the Philadelphia Gazette by Barron under a pseudonym. (Box-folder 8:1-84)
  - Letter - S. Southard, Washington, to Com. James Barron, 26 January 1828., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 8:1)
    Introducing Capt. Basil Hall of the British Navy.
  - Letter - J.N. Reynolds, Washington, to Com. James Barron, Gosport, Virginia, 18 March 1828., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 8:2)
    News that he has received an appropriation of $50,000 from the Congress for an exploration.
  - A statement - made by Midshipman Hunter, 5 April 1828., 3 pages. ADr. (Box-folder 8:3)
    Re: the drowning of Mr. Slidwell, Mr. Rodgers, and Mr. Harrison.
  - Letter - J. Boyle to Com. James Barron, Gosport, 15 April 1828., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 8:4)
    Appreciation for an introduction.
  - Letter - Com. L. Warrington, Washington, to Commodore James Barron, U.S. Navy Yard, Gosport, Virginia, 23 April 1828., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 8:5)
    Introducing Wm. Barrister.
  - Application - Anthony H. Timmons, Philadelphia, to Commodore James Barron, 4 May 1828., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 8:6)
    Application to serve as a midshipman under Barron.
  - Letter - C. Selder, Washington, to Comm. James Barron, Norfolk, 14 May 1828., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 8:7)
    Re: his son who is to report to Barron for service.
  - Letter - John Cowper, Washington, to Commodore James Barron, Norfolk, 31 May 1828., 1 page. PL. (Box-folder 8:8)
    Re: claims under the Treaty of Ghent.
  - Letter - J. Adlum, near Georgetown, to Commodore James Barron, Gosport, Virginia, 11 June 1828., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 8:9)
    Re: shipments of wine.
  - Draft of letter - from J[ames] B[arron] to General Lafayette, 1-6 August 1828., 1 page. ADrS. (Box-folder 8:10)
    Enclosed with a pamphlet on dry rot (now lost).
  - Request - Frances Renshaw, Philadelphia, to Comre. James Barron, Gosport, Virginia, 7 August 1828., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 8:11)
    Request that her letters be forwarded to her son who is serving on a ship in the Pacific.
  - Request - W. Bainbridge, Philadelphia, to Commodore [James] Barron, Norfolk, 6 August 1828., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 8:12)
    Request for dimensions of the moveable crane invented by Barron.
  - Request - W. Bainbridge, Philadelphia, to Commodore [James] Barron, Norfolk, 21 August 1828., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 8:13)
    Request that Midshipman Joyner return to the Department.
  - Request - William Burke, Richmond, to Commodore James Barron, Gosport, 26 October 1828., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 8:14)
    Request for information on a "Denmark stove."
  - Recommendation - W. Bainbridge, Philadelphia, to James Barron, Norfolk, 31 October 1828., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 8:15)
    Recommendation for Barry Hayes.
  - Letter - C.D. Brodie, Pensacola, to Commodore James Barron, Norfolk, 2 November 1828., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 8:16)
    Commending the ship's ventilators invented by Barron.
  - Appointment - Samuel Southard, Navy Department, to Commo. James Barron, Norfolk, 5 November 1828., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 8:17)
    Appointment of Barron to the command of the U.S. Frigate Guerriere, flagship of the Pacific Fleet.
  - Request - [James Barron] to the Secretary of the Navy, [Samuel Southard], 6 November 1828., 1 page. ADr. (Box-folder 8:18)
    Asking to be excused from Pacific Command because of his business in establishing claims for his father's Bounty Lands.
  - Letter - Peter Herbert, Portsmouth, Virginia, to Comme. James Barron, Gosport, 8 November 1828., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 8:19)
    Re: the curative values of wearing a steel plate next to the body.
  - Request - James Barron, Gosport, to Samuel L. Southard, Secretary of the Navy, Washington, 8 November 1828., 1 page. Cop of ALS. (Box-folder 8:20-21)
    Request that Southard, Secretary of the Navy, revoke his orders for Barron to assume command of the Guerriere.
    Incomplete copy of the above is located in folder 21. ADr. 1 page.
  - Letter - Andrew Jackson, Hermitage, to Commodore James Barron, Norfolk, 14 November 1828., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 8:22)
    Introduction of Midshipman Petway.
  - Letter - Benjamin Homans, Washington, to Commo. James Barron, Norfolk, 15 November 1828., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 8:23)
    Re: Barron's refusal of the command of the Guerriere.
  - Letter - Capt. Alex Claxton, U.S. Ship Hornet, New York, to Commodore James Barron, Gosport, Virginia, 19 November 1828., 3 pages. ALS,C. (Box-folder 8:24)
    Marked "Private." Re: an epidemic of yellow fever on his ship which he attributes to the removal of the bellows air pump which had been removed from his ship at the last overhaul. "It is the invention of Commo. Barron... I consider it a thorough safe guard from local fever, and shall not willingly go to sea without one."
  - Letter - C.D. Brodie, Pensacola, to Commodore James Barron, Norfolk, 13 December 1828., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 8:25)
    Congratulations to Barron On the election of his friend Andrew Jackson as President of the U.S.; news of events and ships in the Pensacola Navy Yard.
  - Letter - D. Randolph, near Yorktown, to Commodore [James]Barron, Navy Yard, Gosport, 20 December 1828., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 8:26)
    Personal matters.
  - Letter - J. Rodney, Washington, to Com. J[ames] Barron, 28 January 1829., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 8:27)
  - Letter - Constantine Smith to Commodore James Barron, 13 February 1829., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 8:28)
    Smith, a former Marine, writes for "a Common pension in the country of my adoption," thanks Barron and Lieut. Pendergast for their kindness to him, and sends greetings to Gen'l Andrew Jackson and his nephew Maj. Andrew J. Donaldson.
  - Letter - Dr. P[hilip] Barraud, Norfolk, to Commodore [James] Barron, Washington, 21 February 1829., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 8:29)
    A tumor that has been removed from Barron's son-in-law Pendergrass, and Re: Barron's visit with "your old Favorite General" (Pres. Jackson).
  - Folder 30 currently does not exist in this collection.
  - Letter - Miles King, Norfolk, to Commodore James Barron, Navy Yard, Gosport, 19 May 1829., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 8:31)
    Re: a delivery of stone on the orders of Commo. Warrington.
  - Letter - James Barron, Commandant's Office, U.S. Navy Yard, Gosport, [Virginia], to Lieutenant Joseph Smoot, U.S. Navy Yard, Gosport, 23 May 1829., 4 pages. (Box-folder 8:32)
    A strong letter of censure for Smoot's actions in the Yard.
  - Folder 33 currently does not exist in this collection.
  - Letter - Lewis McLane, Wilmington, Del., to James Barron, U.S. Navy, Norfolk, and reply, 29 May, 2 June 1829., 2 pages. Al S,R. (Box-folder 8:34)
    A call for the repayment of a loan made by the father of McLane; Barron's reply is copied on the reverse.
  - Orders - Frank[li]n Buchanan, U.S. Ship Natchez, New York, to Commo. James Barron, Comm. Naval Station, Norfolk, 8 June 1829., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 8:35)
    Re: his orders to report to the Constellation, under the command of Barron.
  - Orders - H. Paulding, Philadelphia, to Commodore James Barron, Norfolk, 8 June 1829., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 8:36)
    Re: his orders to report to Barron for duty on the Constellation.
  - Letter - Mary [Holt], Williamsburg, to Commodore James Barron, Norfolk, 23 June 1829., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 8:37)
    Re: gossip regarding them and Barron's romantic interest elsewhere.
  - Request - Benj[ami]n King, Washington, to Commodore James Barron, Gosport, Virginia, 3 August 1829., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 8:38)
    Requesting help in his attempt to receive another commission in the Navy.
  - Recommendation - Newton Keene, Alexandria, to Commodore James Barron, Gosport, 25 August 1829., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 8:39)
    Asking a recommendation to the President [of the U.S.].
  - Request - P. Hansen, St. Croix, to Captain Enoch Choate, Norfolk, 2 September 1829., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 8:40)
    Request for help in placing the son of Hansen in a U.S. Mercantile House, and asking the assistance of Commo. Barron.
  - Complaint - [James Barron], Commandants Office, U.S. Navy Yard, Gosport, to Commodore John Rodgers, Pres. of the Navy Board, Washington, D.C., 5 September 1829., 3 pages. ADr. (Box-folder 8:41)
    Complaint regarding a letter received from Rodgers and defense of his own position in regard to material for building at the Navy Yard.
  - Letter - W[illia]m P. Williamson, New York, to Commodore James Barron, 19 September 1829., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 8:42)
    Sent with a tobacco box which was to be a gift for Gen'l Jackson.
  - Letter - Tho[mas] G. Broughton to Commodore James Barron, Navy Yard, Gosport, 1 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 8:43)
    Re: cotton duck.
  - Letter - Dr. P[hilip] Barraud to Commodore [James] Barron, 9 November 1829., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 8:44)
    Regrets that he is unable to accept invitation.
  - Letter - [James Barron] to J.H. Eaton, 20 November 1829., 1 page. ADr. (Box-folder 8:45)
    Re: something, which Eaton has requested, unnamed.
  - Letter - Capt. Ch[arle]s G.B. Thompson, U.S S. Guerriere, at sea, to Commodore James Barron, Norfolk, 3 December 1829., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 8:46)
    En route to Chile where a revolution is reported; and Re: a difficulty with the ship St. Peter, at sea.
  - Receipt - from the Patent Office, covering a plough invented by Commodore Barron, 18 December 1829., AD. (Box-folder 8:47)
  - Printed report - of awards to inventors of the City of Philadelphia from "John Scott's Legacy.", [1829]., 2 pages. PM. (Box-folder 8:48)
  - Letterbook - copies of correspondence of Commo. James Barron, Commandant's Office, United States Navy Yard, Gosport, Virginia 1829-1831., 112 pages used. AV. (Box-folder 8:49)
    The copies of letters are written in Barron's hand and are signed, and cover the period from 14 May 1829 through 17 May 1831.
  - Request - James Monroe, Steamboat Potomac, to Commodore [James] Barron, Norfolk, 11 January 1830., ALS. (Box-folder 8:50a)
    Request that Barron send relief, for their boat is stuck on a sand bar at the Point of Shoals.
  - Request - James Monroe, Steamboat Potomac, to Commodore [James] Barron, Navy Yard, 12 January 1830., ALS. (Box-folder 8:50b)
    Written at "4 o'clock in the morning" a second appeal for relief.
  - Letter - James Monroe, Washington, to Commodore J[ames] Barron, Norfolk, Virginia, 18 January 1830., ALS. (Box-folder 8:50c)
    A letter of appreciation for Barron's "kindness and good offices."
  - Notice - A. Kendall, Treasury Department, to Com. James Barron, Norfolk, 3 February 1830., 1 page. PALS. (Box-folder 8:51)
    Notice of pay due the late John P. Tuttle on the 11th June 1827, the day he died.
  - Letter - Capt. E.P. Kennedy, Washington, to Comore. James Barron, Gosport, Virginia, 1 March 1830., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 8:52)
    Re: the settling of claims, the Navy Bill, and the trial of Creighton.
  - Letter - Capt. E.P. Kennedy, Washington, to Comore. James Barron, Gosport, 15 March 1830., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 8:53)
    Re: activities of Tyler and Eaton.
  - Letter - Capt. E.P. Kennedy, Washington, to Comore. James Barron, Gosport, 17 March 1830., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 8:54)
    Re: the death of Commo. Chauncy, and threat of assassination of Van Buren.
  - Letter - E.P. Kennedy, Washington, to Comore. James Barron, Gosport, 7 April 1830., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 8:55)
    Re: the appointment of Kennedy to command the Frigate U. States on a two-year cruise, and of the opposition of Tazewell to the Navy Bill.
  - [Genl.] Winfield Scott, New York, to Commodore [James] Barron, Norfolk, 19 April 1820., ALS. (Box-folder 8:56)
    Introducing Midshipman Pitcher, son of the Governor of New York.
  - Amos Kendall, Treasury Department, to Com. James Barron, Commanding Navy Yard, Norfolk, June, July 1830., 2 letters. ALsS. (Box-folder 8:57)
    Re: supplies received at the Navy Yard.
  - Letter - Capt. Beverley Kennon, Commandant's Office, Navy Yard, Gosport, Virginia to Commodore [James] Barron, 28 July 1830., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 8:58)
    Reports that he has received orders to transfer to the Brazil station.
  - Letter - [James Barron], Gosport, to "Cleveland at Havanah." 4 August 1830., 1 page. ADr. (Box-folder 8:59)
    Re: the death of Barron's grandson, son of Mrs. [Jane Barron] Hope.
  - Letter - L. Baldwin, Charleston Navy Yard, [Massachuetts], to Commodore James Barron, Navy Yard, Norfolk, Virginia, 1 September 1830., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 8:60)
    Re: the cork cutter invented by Barron.
  - Appeal - Joseph Pulitzay, Malta, to Commodore James Barron, U.S. Navy, 2 September 1830., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 8:61)
    An appeal to Barron to intercede with the President against the dismissal of the U.S. Consul in Malta.
  - Letter - James Barron, Gosport, to George Law, Baltimore, 28 September 1830., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 8:62)
    Re: information desired from Commo. Sinclair.
  - Letter - J. Murdaugh, Richmond, to Commodore James Barron, Navy Yard, Gosport, 3 October 1830., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 8:63)
    Re: standards of Army and Navy rank.
  - Letter - Capt. Edm. P. Kennedy, on the Brandywine off Cape Horn, to Como. J[ames] Barron, Navy Yd., Gosport, 22 October 1830., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 8:64)
    Re: Barron's fixtures on the ship.
  - Letter - J[ames] B[arron] to W[illia]m Maury, 28 October 1830., 1 page. ADrS. (Box-folder 8:65)
    Re: some invention.
  - Letter - Robert S. Garrett, Tappahannock Collector's Office, to Capt. James Barron, U.S. Navy, Norfolk, 15 November 1830., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 8:66)
    Re: the purchase of a boat.
  - Petition - of James Barron to Martin Van Buren, Secretary of State of the United States, 16 November 1830., 3 pages. ADS. (Box-folder 8:67a)
    Application for a patent on a fan.
  - Note - "From Janey Barron Hope's scrapbook.", 1 page. AN. (Box-folder 8:67b)
    Re: Barron's cork cutter, his automatic fan; and recollections of her father Re: Barron's command office the Norfolk Navy Yard.
  - Letter - [James Barron] "To the President... on the dock.", 30 November 1830., 1 page. ADr. (Box-folder 8:68)
  - A statement - regarding a controversy between Commo. [J.D.] Elliott and Capt. Dallas, 22 and 27 March 1831., 3 pages. ADr. (Box-folder 8:69)
    Dated at Pensacola, signed by W[illia]m H. Chase and Tho[mas] Wright.
  - Request - Charles Ellery, Brooklyn, New York, to Commodore James Barron, Gosport, Virginia, 30 March 1831., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 8:70)
    Requesting a personal commendation, which might serve to influence the President in reversing a court martial sentence.